<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title><![CDATA[The UI Lab]]></title><description><![CDATA[Quick tutorials for UI design mastery.]]></description><link>https://www.theuilab.co/</link><image><url>https://www.theuilab.co/favicon.png</url><title>The UI Lab</title><link>https://www.theuilab.co/</link></image><generator>Ghost 5.46</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 May 2023 11:54:07 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.theuilab.co/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Design an effective paywall]]></title><description><![CDATA[Quick tips to help you design a paywall that is right for your product and effective at converting customers into paying ones.]]></description><link>https://www.theuilab.co/design-an-effective-paywall/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6402bef6b3ee6a003d5fe39c</guid><category><![CDATA[Paywall Design]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gareth]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 04:45:44 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2023/03/paywall-1.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2023/03/paywall-1.png" alt="Design an effective paywall"><p></p><p>Paywalls are the backbone of paid products. They are the critical point that people who potentially want to buy something from you will encounter the option to do so. They should be simple to explore, clear, helpful, and hopefully &#x2013; exciting. </p><p>To design a paywall that will convert your users into paying customers, there are a few important things you should take into account. You&apos;ll want to...</p><ol><li>Understand your audience</li><li>Choose the right paywall model</li><li>Clarify any requirements</li><li>Observe what others are doing</li></ol><p>Let&apos;s jump into the first one - understanding your audience, and why that matters.</p><h2 id="understand-your-audience">Understand Your Audience</h2><p>No two paywalls are the same. Or at least, no two paywalls <em>should </em>be the same. Knowing, or at least having some idea, of who you&apos;re designing for is important. </p><p>I won&apos;t spend time going into the importance of user research, defining personas, or mapping user journeys right now, but what is important to know is that different people respond differently to different things.</p><p>Mind-blowing, I know.</p><p>But the crux of this is that, as a user, your state of mind and self-image describe exactly if a paywall will speak to you or not. And speaking to you means conveying if you&apos;re in the right place, that this is value worth paying for, and that you&apos;ll feel good and not like crap after giving someone else your money.</p><p>And this effect will source differently for different people.</p><p>Imagine, for example, two different people: the busy executive assistant purchasing a private jet service for their ego-driven boss, and a stay-at-home parent signing up for a grocery delivery service.</p><p>Think about their motivations. What&apos;s important to them? And crucially, when they&apos;re evaluating their purchase, how do they want it to make them <em>feel</em>? </p><p>When you begin to answer those questions for <em>your </em>audience, it becomes clear that recycling designs will come with varying mileage.</p><p>Designing effectively is important. And for paid products, the paywall is where it&apos;s at. It&apos;s you, the person who has something valuable to sell, meeting the customer in the exact moment that they may want to purchase something valuable from you. And in that moment, you&apos;d better be dressed to the 9&apos;s. As they say.</p><p>So as you move forward in your paywall journey, keep that in mind. When you have an idea of who will be seeing, and evaluating, if your product is worth their money, it&apos;s time to choose which model makes sense for your product.</p><h2 id="choose-a-model">Choose a model</h2><p>There are a few different types of paywalls that you might use depending on the type of content you&apos;re pay-walling and your user behaviors.</p><p>In a nutshell, the different models are:</p><h3 id="hard-paywall">Hard paywall</h3><p>This type of paywall blocks users from consuming any content before paying. Typically this is most effective for brands that have high user awareness, ie, many of your potential customers will be well aware of and decided-on the value of your paid offering.</p><h3 id="freemium">Freemium</h3><p>In a freemium model, some content is free, and some is paid and locked away. This can be beneficial in that it lets your potential customers &quot;sample&quot; the quality of your product before buying. However, it can also mean that people who are less engaged may never purchase.</p><h3 id="metered">Metered</h3><p>Under this model, a user is allowed a certain quanity of content before they are blocked. This likely results in users getting the benefits of a freemium paywall, but with content of their choosing, which may lead to higher pre-purchase engagement, leading to potentially higher overall conversion.</p><h3 id="dynamic">Dynamic</h3><p>The dynamic model is a form of the metered paywall that behaves uniquely per user. Ie, if the data indicates you&apos;re an engaged user, it may trigger a paywall at a different point than if you seem to be less engaged and therefore less likely to purchase down the road if not prompted sooner.</p><p><strong>Why it&apos;s important</strong></p><p>The reason it&apos;s important to take stock of your paywall model is that it is a product decision that needs to be made before you start designing, and one that will also most likely very much define success for, and inform, the resulting design.</p><p>For the sake of this article, let&apos;s assume that the product decisions have been made, and that you&apos;ve selected your paywall model, and are now just concerned about the presentation of your product offerings.</p><p>It&apos;s time to figure out exactly what information you need to deal with in the design. The next section will help you identify those requirements, and more importantly, start thinking of questions you&apos;ll need to get answers to before you jump into the design.</p><h2 id="clarify-requirements">Clarify requirements</h2><p>This is where it&apos;s helpful to make a list of everything you need in your design.</p><p>Questions you might want answers to eventually might include:</p><ul><li>Are there different product offerings or price tiers with distinct benefits or levels of access?</li><li>If so, how many are there, and what are they?</li><li>Are certain product offerings more important than others?</li><li>Is there existing copy or imagery that is non-negotiable and needs to be included? (for example, legal disclaimers)</li><li>Are you offering different payment periods? Do they affect the cost (is there a discount for a specific payment period?)</li><li>Do you know anything about existing customers? For example - which seems to resonate the most with your existing users?</li><li>If not, which would you imagine might?</li><li>Is there any functionality you need to feature?</li></ul><p>Once you get your requirements as close to crystal clear as possible (there&apos;s always some give and take during the design process, but establishing as much of this up front as possible helps streamline things down the road,) you&apos;re ready to start designing.</p><h2 id="observe-observe-observe">Observe, observe, observe</h2><p>There are many successful products out there doing things right. While I&apos;m not advocating for copying a design piece for piece, learning and <em>understanding </em>the underlying mechanics of what makes successful paywalls successful is the most effective thing you can do to get an idea of how you should design yours.</p><p>Take the pieces that seem to be working well, apply them to your audience and brand, and the result will be something bespoke and effective.</p><p>Some paywalls that have created massive success for their companies:</p><h3 id="tinder-gold">Tinder Gold</h3><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2023/03/image.png" class="kg-image" alt="Design an effective paywall" loading="lazy" width="1135" height="1689" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2023/03/image.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2023/03/image.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2023/03/image.png 1135w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Photo credit: <strong>Maverick4840 (reddit)</strong></figcaption></figure><p></p><p></p><h3 id="canva">Canva</h3><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2023/03/image-1.png" class="kg-image" alt="Design an effective paywall" loading="lazy" width="800" height="1732" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2023/03/image-1.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2023/03/image-1.png 800w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Photo credit: www.namiml.com</figcaption></figure><h3 id="buzzfeed">Buzzfeed</h3><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2023/03/image-2.png" class="kg-image" alt="Design an effective paywall" loading="lazy" width="800" height="1626" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2023/03/image-2.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2023/03/image-2.png 800w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Photo credit: www.namiml.com</figcaption></figure>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[6 Figma Features That Will Save You a Ton of Time]]></title><description><![CDATA[These Figma pro tips will save you a ton of time and help you become a faster and more confident designer.]]></description><link>https://www.theuilab.co/6-figma-timesavers/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6363f2e16b70c6003de29321</guid><category><![CDATA[Figma]]></category><category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gareth]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 00:50:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/Figma-Timesavers-5.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/Figma-Timesavers-5.png" alt="6 Figma Features That Will Save You a Ton of Time"><p>I was intimidated the first time I had to use Figma. Before Figma, my UI design world existed within Sketch, Adobe XD, even sometimes Adobe Illustrator.</p><p>Figma was a completely different way of doing things; all the panels and tools were in different places, it almost felt <em>empty </em>in a way, not to mention all of the sudden I was designing collaboratively live with other people.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/looking-around.gif" class="kg-image" alt="6 Figma Features That Will Save You a Ton of Time" loading="lazy" width="498" height="247"><figcaption>Hey uh. Where are the text tools?</figcaption></figure><p>Over time, I&apos;ve learned a lot of the hidden and nuanced functionality built into Figma that makes design a <em>lot </em>easier. Almost exclusively because of all the little things, I went from being a skeptical adopter to a strong advocate.</p><p><strong>These are some of my favorite hidden or semi-hidden functionalities that I use all the time:</strong></p><ol><li>Use an 8 point grid</li><li>Change the nudge size to match your grid</li><li>Use the special Paste tools</li><li>Quick-select an object within a group</li><li>Use Selection Colors to change all instances of a color</li><li>Copy and paste layer effects</li></ol><h2 id="use-a-grid-or-layout-system">Use a grid or layout system</h2><p>The basic principle of using a grid is to use a multiple of a single number to dictate all sizing, spacing, padding, margins. </p><p><strong>I&apos;m a big fan of 8pt grid </strong>- it&apos;s very commonly used and friendly to many common screen sizes.</p><p>This means <strong>all of your sizes, spacing, padding, and margins will be multiples of 8</strong>: (8, 16, 24, 32, 40, 48, and so on.)</p><p>I&apos;ll spare you the snobby lecture and hot-take on why true designers do or don&apos;t use grids. This is a turtleneck-free zone.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/giphy-5.gif" class="kg-image" alt="6 Figma Features That Will Save You a Ton of Time" loading="lazy" width="480" height="270"><figcaption>We get it. Grids are divine.</figcaption></figure><p>In reality, the reasons why you should use a grid aren&apos;t actually that complicated. <strong>The benefits of using a grid come down to this:</strong></p><ol><li>Less time spent measuring</li><li>Less guessing and remembering how much padding or spacing to use in new scenarios</li><li>Less time and energy spent &quot;feeling out&quot; what looks good </li><li>Fewer &quot;design typo&quot; type mistakes</li><li>More time spent confidently designing</li></ol><p>Have you ever spent time trying to split a bill up amongst friends in your head, missed something or realized you weren&apos;t able to hold one of the numbers in your head, and then had to go back and do it all over again? No one enjoys this process. Not you, not the other people at the table. This is what calculators are for.</p><p>Grids are like calculators for design. They make it easier for you to be consistent when doing common, repetitive, and BORING, but <em>important,</em> stuff &#x2014; like making your padding and sizing consistent. </p><p>Who wants to spend <em>more</em> time making sure their padding is consistent? No one ever.</p><p>Who messes it up or misses things when they try to do repetitive and focus-intensive tasks manually? Everyone always.</p><p><strong>Here&apos;s the thing: you shouldn&apos;t feel bad about being inconsistent in the first place, but you <em>should</em> strive to be consistent.</strong></p><p>We are not calculators &#x2014; we&apos;re human beings; we&apos;re fleshy, squishy, messy creatures. We <em>use </em>calculators. And we also didn&apos;t evolve in symmetrical, digital spaces.</p><p>Our brains just weren&apos;t made to accurately create dozens, hundreds, or even thousands of perfectly-spaced objects. When you think about it, it&apos;s pretty <em>weird</em>. </p><p>Unless you&apos;re some kind of strange and questionable personality, it&apos;s hard <em>and</em> it&apos;s uninteresting to do this kind of work while maintaining your accuracy, which is a great combo if you want to get less done and hate the time you spent doing it and end up with a lot of mistakes.</p><p>Not to mention if you&apos;re the one building what you or someone else designed, you <em>also </em>don&apos;t want to be spending your time guessing, measuring, or having to ask the designer every time something isn&apos;t clear.</p><p>And this kind of spacing isn&apos;t a good look or helpful for anyone:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/messy-sizing.png" class="kg-image" alt="6 Figma Features That Will Save You a Ton of Time" loading="lazy" width="1754" height="622" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/11/messy-sizing.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/11/messy-sizing.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1600/2022/11/messy-sizing.png 1600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/messy-sizing.png 1754w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>13.73 pixels. Nice.</p><p>On the other hand, this is very clean, consistent, and reliable:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/clean-sizing.png" class="kg-image" alt="6 Figma Features That Will Save You a Ton of Time" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="599" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/11/clean-sizing.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/11/clean-sizing.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1600/2022/11/clean-sizing.png 1600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/clean-sizing.png 2078w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p><strong>When you design with a system, there&apos;s less guesswork in the process for everyone. </strong>That means less time spent doing the type of work that your brain is terrible at not messing up. </p><p>So, use a grid. I recommend using an 8 point grid. You&apos;ll be happier for it now <em>and </em>in the future when you come back to your designs, engineers will be happier for it, and your designs will be better.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/200-4.gif" class="kg-image" alt="6 Figma Features That Will Save You a Ton of Time" loading="lazy" width="267" height="200"></figure><h2 id="change-your-nudge-and-big-nudge-size-to-match-your-grid-system">Change your nudge and big nudge size to match your grid system</h2><!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>In Figma, <code>nudging</code> allows you to move selected elements in predictable intervals by selecting an element and pressing an arrow key.</p>
<p>A <code>big nudge</code> lets you move things in larger intervals by pressing <code>Shift</code> + any of the arrow keys <code>&#x2190; &#x2192; &#x2191; &#x2193;</code>.</p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown--><p><strong>The default big nudge size is 10px.</strong> You can change that, to, say, match your grid size! <strong>I set mine to 8px because I use an 8pt grid, and it makes my life so much easier.</strong></p><p>To change your nudge size:</p><!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><ol>
<li>Click the <code>Figma menu icon</code></li>
<li>Select <code>Preferences</code></li>
<li>All the way at the bottom, select <code>Nudge Amount</code></li>
</ol>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown--><ol><li></li></ol><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/change-big-nudge-size.gif" class="kg-image" alt="6 Figma Features That Will Save You a Ton of Time" loading="lazy" width="800" height="492" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/11/change-big-nudge-size.gif 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/change-big-nudge-size.gif 800w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Once you do this and adopt an 8pt grid system, you will be absolutely <em>flying </em>on your padding and sizing.</p><h2 id="paste-tools-in-figma">Paste tools in Figma</h2><p>Figma has some nifty and useful pasting functionality that were brought in from other tools. They&apos;re a nice little speed boost to your workflow, especially if you or your team aren&apos;t using a design system.</p><h3 id="paste-here">Paste here</h3><!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p><code>Paste here</code> lets you paste an object directly where your cursor is, like this:</p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown--><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/paste-here.gif" class="kg-image" alt="6 Figma Features That Will Save You a Ton of Time" loading="lazy" width="600" height="395" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/paste-here.gif 600w"></figure><p>I use this all the time when I want to tell Figma <em>exactly </em>where to paste something, without it following another higher-level rule (for example, pasting in the center of the screen.)</p><h3 id="paste-to-replace">Paste to replace </h3><p>This is my absolute favorite. It&apos;s both simple and incredibly flexible, and therefore, powerful. Paste to replace allows you to replace selected elements, with elements you copied to the clipboard. </p><p>Here&apos;s how you do it:</p><ol><li>Copy the element</li><li>Select element(s) you want to replace</li><li>Past to replace:</li></ol><!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p><strong>Mac:</strong> <code>CMD</code> <code>Option</code> <code>Shift</code> <code>V</code><br>
<strong>Windows:</strong> <code>Ctrl</code> <code>Alt</code> <code>Shift</code> <code>V</code></p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown--><p>You can do this to replace one element:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/paste-to-replace-1.gif" class="kg-image" alt="6 Figma Features That Will Save You a Ton of Time" loading="lazy" width="600" height="395" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/paste-to-replace-1.gif 600w"></figure><p>Or several ungrouped elements at once, which is a <em>massive </em>time-saver:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/paste-to-replace-multiple.gif" class="kg-image" alt="6 Figma Features That Will Save You a Ton of Time" loading="lazy" width="600" height="395" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/paste-to-replace-multiple.gif 600w"></figure><p>The more you use this one, the more you&apos;ll find creative ways to save you time. It&apos;s great.</p><h2 id="select-objects-within-a-group">Select Objects Within a Group</h2><p>When you have a lot of grouped objects, it can be tiresome to double-click your way into selecting the element you want. Fortunately, there&apos;s a shortcut.</p><!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>All you have to do is hold <code>Cmd</code> if you&apos;re on Mac, or <code>Ctrl</code> if you&apos;re on Windows.</p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown--><p>Check it out:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/select-within-group.gif" class="kg-image" alt="6 Figma Features That Will Save You a Ton of Time" loading="lazy" width="600" height="406" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/select-within-group.gif 600w"></figure><p></p><h2 id="use-selection-colors-to-speed-run-mass-color-changes">Use Selection Colors to speed-run mass color changes</h2><p>I love this one. Especially if you&apos;re not using a design system, the ability to quickly change colors of multiple ungrouped elements on the fly is huge. This means you can adjust multiple elements at the same time, without having to select each one individually: </p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/selection-colors.gif" class="kg-image" alt="6 Figma Features That Will Save You a Ton of Time" loading="lazy" width="600" height="375" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/selection-colors.gif 600w"></figure><p>On a larger scale, it means you can select a frame and change every instance of that color on the whole screen:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/selection-colors-frame.gif" class="kg-image" alt="6 Figma Features That Will Save You a Ton of Time" loading="lazy" width="600" height="468" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/selection-colors-frame.gif 600w"></figure><p>So much time saved by not going into each element and changing its color. The next major level up of this boost is to use a design system, which I&apos;ll cover in another lesson.</p><p>And that brings me to the final tip for this list:</p><h2 id="copy-and-paste-layer-effects">Copy and Paste Layer Effects</h2><p>Layer effects are things like drop shadows, background blurs, layer blurs, and so on. They&apos;re useful and common in UI design, so it&apos;s valuable to know how to reproduce them quickly without having to remake them or remember your custom values.</p><p>Once again, you can actually save and reuse layer styles by creating a Figma library (aka reusable design system,) but for the purpose of this post I&apos;ll show you how to quickly copy and paste them across elements.</p><p><strong>All you have to do to paste layer effects is is:</strong></p><!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><ol>
<li>Select the layer whose styles you want to copy</li>
<li>Click the space just to the left of the effect you want to copy (you can use <code>Shift</code> + <code>click</code> to select multiple)</li>
<li>Use <code>Cmd/Ctrl</code> + <code>C</code> to copy the effect</li>
<li>Select the new layer, and use <code>Cmd/Ctrl</code> + <code>V</code> to paste the effect onto it</li>
</ol>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown--><p><strong>Which looks like this:</strong></p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/paste-layer-effects.gif" class="kg-image" alt="6 Figma Features That Will Save You a Ton of Time" loading="lazy" width="600" height="384" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/paste-layer-effects.gif 600w"></figure><!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>You can also copy and paste layer effects via the <code>right click menu</code> or by using <code>Cmd/Ctrl</code> + <code>Option/Alt</code> + <code>C</code> and <code>Cmd/Ctrl</code> + <code>Option/Alt</code> + <code>V</code>. It&apos;s worth noting, however, that this will also copy other properties like corner radius:</p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown--><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/copy-effects-right-click.gif" class="kg-image" alt="6 Figma Features That Will Save You a Ton of Time" loading="lazy" width="600" height="373" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/copy-effects-right-click.gif 600w"></figure><p>I use all of these almost every single day doing design work. Figma is loaded with a ton of optimizations like this, so dig around, try things, and you may discover even more little powerups to your workflow.</p><p>For now, I hope this has been helpful to you in your UI design journey!</p><p>&#x26A1;</p><p><em>Was this article helpful? You can support me by <a href="https://www.buymeacoffee.com/uilab?ref=theuilab.co">buying me a coffee</a>! (I love coffee.)</em></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How To Use Figma Mirror To Design on Your Phone]]></title><description><![CDATA[And why using Figma on your phone will improve your UI design.]]></description><link>https://www.theuilab.co/how-to-use-figma-mirror/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">635eec5dc97b71003d4dd637</guid><category><![CDATA[Figma]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gareth]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 16:13:34 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/FIGMA-MIRROR.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/FIGMA-MIRROR.png" alt="How To Use Figma Mirror To Design on Your Phone"><p>The Figma Mirror app, now just called Figma, is a powerful tool to have at your disposal as a UI designer.</p><p>If you&apos;re designing mobile apps and you&apos;re not designing on your phone, you need to start <em>immediately</em>. It will &#x2014; I promise I&apos;m not exaggerating &#x2014; make you a better UI designer.</p><p>When you design an app for a phone, <em>on</em> a phone, you&apos;re removing one more layer of interpretation that your brain has to do to imagine it in context.</p><p><strong>The closer you can get to creating a 1:1 relationship between the context you&apos;re designing <em>for</em> and the context you&apos;re designing <em>in</em>, the better your designs will be.</strong></p><p>For those of you who have used an earlier Wacom or similar device and switched to an iPad Pro or similar device (again: once the technology of the iPad-like-device became close enough to a 1:1 experience,) it&apos;s like going from this:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/firos-nv-58c1dnakdRQ-unsplash.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use Figma Mirror To Design on Your Phone" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="1500" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/firos-nv-58c1dnakdRQ-unsplash.jpg 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/firos-nv-58c1dnakdRQ-unsplash.jpg 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1600/2022/10/firos-nv-58c1dnakdRQ-unsplash.jpg 1600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w2400/2022/10/firos-nv-58c1dnakdRQ-unsplash.jpg 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>To this:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/cristofer-maximilian-PP1yKpfA4HY-unsplash.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use Figma Mirror To Design on Your Phone" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="1161" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/cristofer-maximilian-PP1yKpfA4HY-unsplash.jpg 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/cristofer-maximilian-PP1yKpfA4HY-unsplash.jpg 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1600/2022/10/cristofer-maximilian-PP1yKpfA4HY-unsplash.jpg 1600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w2400/2022/10/cristofer-maximilian-PP1yKpfA4HY-unsplash.jpg 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>I know there will be diehard Wacom holdouts out there that will come after me for this comment. But. Once the refresh rate and pressure sensitivity of iPads caught up to the point of diminishing returns relative to the Wacom, the iPad provided an objectively better experience overall. </p><p>And this is because it closed the gap across screen quality, pressure levels, and response time, creating a near 1:1 experience for digital drawing and painting.</p><blockquote class="kg-blockquote-alt"><strong>The closer you can get to creating a 1:1 relationship between the context you&apos;re designing <em>for</em> and the context you&apos;re designing <em>in</em>, the better your designs will be.</strong></blockquote><p>In the Figma app, not only can you see the changes you make in the right context (on the phone) as you make them, but you can also interact with your designs as you design them.</p><p>Meaning, if you&apos;re designing an app and you&apos;ve wired up your screens to be interactive, you can use it similar to how you&apos;d use the actual app.</p><p>Even better: this means <em>other people</em> can use the screens you&apos;re working on as if it&apos;s in an actual app, so the feedback you get will <em>also </em>be nearly 1:1 with what it would be if they were using the actual app.</p><p>So without further ado, let&apos;s start out by downloading the Figma app. Here are the respective links for each platform:</p><p><a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/figma-and-figjam/id1152747299?ref=theuilab.co">Figma for iPhone</a></p><p><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.figma.mirror&amp;hl=en_US&amp;gl=US&amp;ref=theuilab.co">Figma for Android</a></p><p><strong>Once you&apos;ve got the app downloaded, you need to know two things:</strong></p><ol><li>It requires you to be signed into the same Figma account on both your phone and computer</li><li>It used to require you to be on the same wi-fi network. Now it doesn&apos;t, but I&apos;d recommend it anyway, since it will use a lot of data otherwise.</li></ol><p>Now that you&apos;re signed into the app and into your Figma account on your computer, you can simply click a frame to select it.</p><p><strong>Important note:</strong> you should use a frame size that matches your phone. This is important because your elements will not be sized correctly if you don&apos;t. If you don&apos;t know, here&apos;s how you set that.</p><p><strong>Why this is important:</strong> imagine designing in a tablet-sized screen size, and then viewing it on your phone: all of those pixels will just be scaled down to fit within the viewport of your phone, so you won&apos;t be getting an accurate read on the sizing of your elements.</p><p><strong>To do this, first select the Frame tool in the upper left. You can also press F on your keyboard. </strong></p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/Frame-tool.png" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use Figma Mirror To Design on Your Phone" loading="lazy" width="904" height="310" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/11/Frame-tool.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/Frame-tool.png 904w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><div class="kg-card kg-callout-card kg-callout-card-green"><div class="kg-callout-emoji">&#x26A1;</div><div class="kg-callout-text">Ps- If you haven&apos;t already, start learning those hotkeys! I was a hold-out for a long time; I&apos;m a naturally mouse-driven computer user. But using hotkeys in combination with my mouse has <em>seriously</em> sped up my workflow.</div></div><p>Once you have the Frame tool selected, check out the top right of the Figma screen. You&apos;ll get a list of frame sizes for common devices:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/Figma-frame-sizes.png" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use Figma Mirror To Design on Your Phone" loading="lazy" width="1784" height="1798" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/11/Figma-frame-sizes.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/11/Figma-frame-sizes.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1600/2022/11/Figma-frame-sizes.png 1600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/Figma-frame-sizes.png 1784w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>They do a pretty good job of updating this list. So check for your phone, and if you can&apos;t find it, I&apos;d recommend creating your own frame sized based on the aspect ratio and dimensions of your phone.</p><p>Ok. Now that we have our frame set up, let&apos;s start mirroring our designs on our phone!</p><p>If you have the Figma app open on your phone, and you&apos;re signed into the right account, just select the frame you want to mirror to have it display on your phone.</p><p><strong>Small pro tip: it&apos;s easier to select the frame if you click near the name:</strong></p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/select-frame.png" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use Figma Mirror To Design on Your Phone" loading="lazy" width="1138" height="846" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/select-frame.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/select-frame.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/select-frame.png 1138w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Click near the name to select a frame.</figcaption></figure><p>The Figma app will detect that you&apos;ve selected a frame and will ask you if you want to mirror it on your device:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-figma-mirror-1.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use Figma Mirror To Design on Your Phone" loading="lazy" width="1065" height="800" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-figma-mirror-1.jpg 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/uilab-figma-mirror-1.jpg 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-figma-mirror-1.jpg 1065w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Select the frame in Figma, and you&apos;ll get a prompt on your phone.</figcaption></figure><p><strong>Alternatively, you can tap on the Mirror tab,</strong> where after selecting the frame, you&apos;ll see an in-line prompt to mirror your selected frame.</p><p>Then in either place, select Mirror, and the frame should display on your device:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-figma-mirror2.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use Figma Mirror To Design on Your Phone" loading="lazy" width="1065" height="800" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-figma-mirror2.jpg 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/uilab-figma-mirror2.jpg 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-figma-mirror2.jpg 1065w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>You can now move elements around in the desktop, and the changes will happen in real time in the Figma mirror app so long as you select the frame.</p><p>This means you have instant feedback as you design.</p><p>I actually set up my phone next to my computer and use it as my primary design &quot;display&quot; when I&apos;m doing UI design for mobile apps, using the desktop app as more of an input to what I&apos;m seeing on my phone:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/figma-mirror-setup.png" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use Figma Mirror To Design on Your Phone" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="1570" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/11/figma-mirror-setup.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/11/figma-mirror-setup.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1600/2022/11/figma-mirror-setup.png 1600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/figma-mirror-setup.png 2230w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Stop looking at my dusty keyboard</figcaption></figure><p>It&apos;s also possible to run prototypes in the Figma app so you can tap around what you&apos;ve designed. The setup process is the same as the one we just did; just make elements into an interactive prototype in Figma, and you&apos;ll be able to see them as you design <em>and </em>tap to use them.</p><p>Once you get the hang of it, using Figma mirror to design on your phone will change how you think about mobile app design. You can start designing as if you are designing an app in real time, rather than designing a picture of an app that will then be built into one.</p><p>It&apos;ll save you time translating your designs to workable sizes, gives you a better sense of how your colors will appear on a modern phone screen, and forces you to consider the usability of your design immediately and proactively rather than retroactively.</p><p>The cherry on top: handing someone a UI designed and having them use it right in front of you is a way more efficient way to get feedback on your designs.</p><p>When you design on your phone, there are fewer layers of interpretation and less suspense-of-disbelief required. Less imagining, and more doing the next thing. </p><p><strong>Bottom line: it will make you more efficient designer overall, and I&apos;d highly recommend it.</strong></p><p>Happy designing! &#x26A1;</p><p><em>Was this article helpful? You can support me by <a href="https://www.buymeacoffee.com/uilab?ref=theuilab.co">buying me a coffee</a>! (I love coffee.)</em></p><hr><p>Fyi, here&apos;s what I use to keep my phone propped up while I&apos;m designing. I like it because:</p><ul><li>You don&apos;t see much of the stand around your phone</li><li>There&apos;s a hole in the back for a charger cable</li><li>It&apos;s metal, so it helps keep your phone cool with all the Figma-ing</li><li>It&apos;s cheap and looks decent</li></ul><div class="kg-card kg-product-card"><div class="kg-product-card-container"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/61u3D5V4I7L._AC_SL1300_.jpg" width="1300" height="1300" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/61u3D5V4I7L._AC_SL1300_.jpg 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/61u3D5V4I7L._AC_SL1300_.jpg 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/61u3D5V4I7L._AC_SL1300_.jpg 1300w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px" class="kg-product-card-image" loading="lazy" alt="How To Use Figma Mirror To Design on Your Phone"><div class="kg-product-card-title-container"><h4 class="kg-product-card-title">Lamicall Cell Phone Stand</h4></div><div class="kg-product-card-description"><p>$9.99</p></div><a href="https://amzn.to/3gVkXNU?ref=theuilab.co" class="kg-product-card-button kg-product-card-btn-accent" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span>Buy on Amazon</span></a></div></div><p></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Create a "Premium" Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)]]></title><description><![CDATA[Learn how to design premium-feeling gold UI elements for your premium tier products in Figma.]]></description><link>https://www.theuilab.co/how-to-make-gold-ui-elements/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">635d9b79c97b71003d4dd389</guid><category><![CDATA[Paywall Design]]></category><category><![CDATA[Visual Design]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gareth]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2022 16:50:28 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2023/03/gold-effect-figma-template.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2023/03/gold-effect-figma-template.png" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)"><p><a href="#use-it-today-%E2%80%93-download-the-template"><strong>Jump to the template&#x1F447;</strong></a></p><p>You know those fancy gold effects you see in app UIs like Robinhood or Tinder?</p><p>Sometimes you&apos;ll see it used for mobile game UIs, for in game currencies, achievements, or awards:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/07b9c960-9036-4ff2-ad44-29cb3097b6a8.png" class="kg-image" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)" loading="lazy" width="972" height="1400" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/07b9c960-9036-4ff2-ad44-29cb3097b6a8.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/07b9c960-9036-4ff2-ad44-29cb3097b6a8.png 972w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Image credit: come on. It&apos;s Candy Crush.</figcaption></figure><p>The use of gold as a color association to create feelings of exclusiveness and richness is one as old as time. Just go to any casino. Think that gold lighting and curtains are a mistake? Nope.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/kvnga-vBWsG91aR_U-unsplash.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="1333" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/kvnga-vBWsG91aR_U-unsplash.jpg 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/kvnga-vBWsG91aR_U-unsplash.jpg 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1600/2022/10/kvnga-vBWsG91aR_U-unsplash.jpg 1600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w2400/2022/10/kvnga-vBWsG91aR_U-unsplash.jpg 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Or how about this credit card from AMEX?</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/NUS000000174_480x304_straight_withname.png.webp" class="kg-image" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)" loading="lazy" width="480" height="304"><figcaption>Don&apos;t pay for credit cards.</figcaption></figure><p>Getting something gold for your money is cashing in (ha) on the age-old color association that <strong>gold is valuable</strong>. Even stuff that just... <em>looks </em>gold. </p><p>That&apos;s one of many tactics that credit card companies employ to get people to pay <em>them</em> to use their card<em>.</em></p><p>In the example below, Tinder uses the gold effect to create a premium feel for people paying for their premium offering, Tinder Gold. </p><p>The app will even modify their UI elements after you&apos;ve purchased Tinder Gold, by placing a gold app icon on your home screen:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/66872661.jpg.webp" class="kg-image" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)" loading="lazy" width="1200" height="900" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/66872661.jpg.webp 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/66872661.jpg.webp 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/66872661.jpg.webp 1200w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>This is done to create the feeling that you&apos;ve purchased a special experience, that you&apos;re a member of a special &quot;VIP&quot; type group. Your app is gold, therefore, you have gold. You&apos;re a gold member.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/gold-member-bailando.gif" class="kg-image" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)" loading="lazy" width="498" height="278"></figure><p><em>ahem</em></p><p>Regardless of the use of color psychology and the endless and important ethical debates that come with design, it&apos;s a cool effect and can be useful to know how to use it in your UI designs. </p><p>You can also use it as a foundation to create other metallic treatments. And it&apos;s also not super difficult to create in Figma.</p><p>With that said...</p><p><strong>There are two primary styles of gold we&apos;ll cover:</strong></p><ol><li>Metallic satin gold</li><li>Polished gold</li></ol><p>And this is what they look like:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/gold-satin-polished-1.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)" loading="lazy" width="1065" height="642" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/gold-satin-polished-1.jpg 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/gold-satin-polished-1.jpg 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/gold-satin-polished-1.jpg 1065w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><h2 id="how-to-create-satin-gold-for-premium-offerings">How to Create Satin Gold for Premium Offerings</h2><p>Satin gold has a more luxurious feel to it, which means it&apos;s well-suited to premium app or websites offerings that want to give their purchasers a sense of luxuriousness or specialness.</p><p>To create a satin gold effect, first let&apos;s create our base shape. To start out, let&apos;s use a rounded rectangle with some really nice corner smoothing, because we like to have fun.</p><p>I used a <strong>240px x 240px</strong> rectangle, and applied <strong>64px corner radius</strong> with <strong>100% corner smoothing </strong>to make it extra sassy:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/create-rectangle.png" class="kg-image" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="1094" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/create-rectangle.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/create-rectangle.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1600/2022/10/create-rectangle.png 1600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/create-rectangle.png 2014w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Sassy as heck</figcaption></figure><p>Then, with this shape selected, select the color picker under Fill and pick the Linear gradient option:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/lineargradient.png" class="kg-image" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="1013" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/lineargradient.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/lineargradient.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1600/2022/10/lineargradient.png 1600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/lineargradient.png 2220w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Now we can start building our gradient. </p><p>For the satin gold effect, we&apos;ll create <strong>3 gradient points by clicking in the empty space above the gradient bar:</strong></p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/add-gradient-point.gif" class="kg-image" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)" loading="lazy" width="600" height="298" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/add-gradient-point.gif 600w"></figure><p>And <strong>set them all to 100% opacity. </strong></p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/3-gradient-points.png" class="kg-image" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="1022" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/3-gradient-points.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/3-gradient-points.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1600/2022/10/3-gradient-points.png 1600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/3-gradient-points.png 2054w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Next, since we want a luxurious gold feel, we&apos;ll select some slightly desaturated gold colors for both ends, and a lighter version or <em>tint </em>of that for the center. I&apos;m using <strong>#EECB84 for the ends </strong>and<strong> #FFE5AE for the center:</strong></p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/gold.png" class="kg-image" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="970" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/gold.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/gold.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1600/2022/10/gold.png 1600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/gold.png 2012w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Ooh, so luxurious.</figcaption></figure><p>Finally, we&apos;ll set the gradient angle, <strong>keeping the handles aligned to the outer bounds of the shape</strong>:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/set-gradient-angle.gif" class="kg-image" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)" loading="lazy" width="600" height="291" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/set-gradient-angle.gif 600w"><figcaption>Annnd shift.</figcaption></figure><p>Wa la! Satin gold.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/satin-gold-1.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)" loading="lazy" width="1065" height="470" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/satin-gold-1.jpg 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/satin-gold-1.jpg 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/satin-gold-1.jpg 1065w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Buy me</figcaption></figure><p>Next, let&apos;s tackle the shinier cousin: polished gold.</p><h2 id="how-to-create-polished-gold-for-game-like-elements">How to Create Polished Gold for Game-Like Elements</h2><p>Polished gold is shiny, fun, and rich, which means it works well applied to components or visual elements like achievements, badges, currency, and anything else you might get as a reward in an app or game.</p><p>To create a polished gold effect, we&apos;ll start with our base shape again, and select linear gradient.</p><p><strong>This time, we&apos;ll create 4 gradient points:</strong></p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/linear-gradient-with-4-points.png" class="kg-image" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)" loading="lazy" width="1998" height="1108" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/linear-gradient-with-4-points.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/linear-gradient-with-4-points.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1600/2022/10/linear-gradient-with-4-points.png 1600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/linear-gradient-with-4-points.png 1998w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>One extra point will make all the difference.</figcaption></figure><p>For the polished gold effect, we want to use a more rich and saturated color palette. This gold should almost feel &quot;juicy&quot; by comparison to the satin gold. Less luxurious, more stimulating.</p><p>For the gradient colors, left to right, I&apos;m using #FDD792, #FEF9EB, #F9C475, and #D68E43.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/polished-gold-gradient-colors.png" class="kg-image" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)" loading="lazy" width="1978" height="1000" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/polished-gold-gradient-colors.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/polished-gold-gradient-colors.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1600/2022/10/polished-gold-gradient-colors.png 1600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/polished-gold-gradient-colors.png 1978w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Nice &apos;n juicy.</figcaption></figure><p>Then, just like the last one, we&apos;ll rotate our gradient angle.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/rotate-polished-gradient.gif" class="kg-image" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)" loading="lazy" width="600" height="298" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/rotate-polished-gradient.gif 600w"></figure><p>We&apos;re still pretty satin-y. And we don&apos;t want any religious groups knocking on our doors, so we&apos;ll take a step back from satin-ism and polish our gold.</p><p><strong>To do this, we&apos;ll change the distribution of the color points.</strong></p><p>Take those two center color handles and move them so close to each other that they no longer fade, but occur immediately after each other:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/polish-that-gold.gif" class="kg-image" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)" loading="lazy" width="600" height="298" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/polish-that-gold.gif 600w"></figure><p>And there we go! Like true alchemists, we&apos;ve made polished gold:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/polished-gold.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)" loading="lazy" width="1065" height="470" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/polished-gold.jpg 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/polished-gold.jpg 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/polished-gold.jpg 1065w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Internet.</figcaption></figure><p>The real magic of these treatments comes out when you start to combine them. For example, if we combine satin and polished gold to create an alternate version of the logo for Tinder Gold, we get some interesting results:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/combined-ooh-ahh.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)" loading="lazy" width="1065" height="642" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/combined-ooh-ahh.jpg 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/combined-ooh-ahh.jpg 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/combined-ooh-ahh.jpg 1065w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Cool looking, but low contrast &#x2014; there&apos;s a reason the real logo is gold on white. Animation could help.</figcaption></figure><p>It&apos;s fun to experiment with different material treatments, but they should be used carefully and sparingly if at all. </p><p>Not all brands reserve space for gold or metallic treatments in the first place. And used in the wrong context or overused, it&apos;s <em>very</em> easy to create something gaudy and garish that actually doesn&apos;t benefit your brand or product.</p><p>So if you&apos;ve made it to the end of this, thanks for joining me. While if I were you, I wouldn&apos;t go off and start making everything gold, learning <em>how</em> to create high quality metallic gradients in Figma is a useful tool to have in your back pocket as a UI designer. </p><p>I&apos;ve used it more than once in my career, and so you may too.</p><p>As always please let me know if I missed something, or you have any feedback on this article. I want to make this the most practical and useful resource for anyone looking to improve their UI design skillset.</p><p>Additionally, if there&apos;s anything you&apos;d like to know how to create in Figma, send it to me in an email and I&apos;d be happy to make a tutorial.</p><p>Happy designing!</p><h2 id="use-it-today-%E2%80%93-download-the-template">Use it today &#x2013; download the template</h2><div class="kg-card kg-product-card"><div class="kg-product-card-container"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2023/03/gold-figma-4.png" width="1600" height="960" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2023/03/gold-figma-4.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2023/03/gold-figma-4.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2023/03/gold-figma-4.png 1600w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px" class="kg-product-card-image" loading="lazy" alt="Create a &quot;Premium&quot; Metallic Gold Effect in Figma (plus template)"><div class="kg-product-card-title-container"><h4 class="kg-product-card-title">Use it now! Get the Golden UI Elements Template ($5)</h4></div><div class="kg-product-card-description"><p>Includes everything you see in this post so you can deconstruct it or use it now.</p></div><a href="https://motivated-trailblazer-2610.ck.page/products/gold-elements-template?ref=theuilab.co" class="kg-product-card-button kg-product-card-btn-accent" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span>Go to Download</span></a></div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow]]></title><description><![CDATA[And why some drop shadows look better than others.]]></description><link>https://www.theuilab.co/create-polished-shadows-in-figma/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">635b06b8c97b71003d4dd005</guid><category><![CDATA[Figma]]></category><category><![CDATA[Visual Design]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gareth]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2022 21:05:20 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/shadows-figma.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/shadows-figma.png" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow"><p>Dropshadows are important in UI design. They can be used to aesthetic ends as well as a functional ends; elements with dropshadows signal to our brains that the element is lifted, and therefore, something that can be pressed.</p><p>This is why buttons often have drop shadows, as well as other elements, especially things like switches, knobs, and dials. If you take a look at Apple&apos;s design system for iOS 16, for example, drop shadows are applied to a specific subset of elements:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/iOS-dropshadows-1.png" class="kg-image" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow" loading="lazy" width="829" height="437" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/iOS-dropshadows-1.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/iOS-dropshadows-1.png 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>This varies to some degree across platforms, but for the most part drop shadows are used strategically and conservatively rather than liberally.</p><p>So why do some dropshadows look wrong, and some look... right?</p><h2 id="ui-law-1-your-brain-expects-digital-things-to-follow-the-laws-of-the-physical-world">UI Law #1: Your brain expects digital things to follow the laws of the physical world</h2><p>For real. </p><p><strong>Although our new digital universe may be entirely man-made, our brains still evaluates digital objects as if they were physical. </strong>This is a core concept of designing for comfort and familiarity in UX Design, UI Design, and Interaction Design.</p><p>And as you start designing, the more you take cues from the physical world when designing your product, the more the natural your product will feel.</p><p>Take, for example, the drop shadows here:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/dropshadow-frontcast.png" class="kg-image" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow" loading="lazy" width="829" height="437" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/dropshadow-frontcast.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/dropshadow-frontcast.png 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>They may not look terrible, but let&apos;s make a small tweak and try this:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/dropshadow-downcast.png" class="kg-image" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow" loading="lazy" width="829" height="437" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/dropshadow-downcast.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/dropshadow-downcast.png 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Better, right? So... why is that? What&apos;s your brain expecting here? </p><p>Welp, it&apos;s kinda funny. <strong>In the absense of another clear light source, it&apos;s expecting the Sun.</strong></p><p>And where&apos;s the Sun relative to... well, everything? Up, of course. In other words...</p><h2 id="cast-your-ui-drop-shadows-down-like-the-sun-is-the-light-source">Cast your UI drop shadows down, like the Sun is the light source</h2><p>Drop shadows, if you decide to use them in your UI, should pretty much always be cast downward<em>. </em>It&apos;s as simple, and silly, as that.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/dropshadow-unclear-lightsource-1.png" class="kg-image" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow" loading="lazy" width="829" height="437" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/dropshadow-unclear-lightsource-1.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/dropshadow-unclear-lightsource-1.png 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>To do this, edit the &quot;Y&quot; value on the shadow in Figma:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/edit-y-value.png" class="kg-image" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow" loading="lazy" width="1016" height="580" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/edit-y-value.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/edit-y-value.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/edit-y-value.png 1016w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>You know how you jump when a monster comes out of nowhere in a thriller movie? This is basically that on a smaller scale. </p><p>We&apos;re not so good at <em>subconsciously </em>knowing what&apos;s real and what&apos;s not, even if we consciously know it isn&apos;t.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/200-3.gif" class="kg-image" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow" loading="lazy" width="265" height="200"><figcaption>Maybe not the movie you pictured, but this had me on the edge of my seat when I was 6.</figcaption></figure><p>So cast your shadows down, because even though there&apos;s no sun... your brain thinks there is.</p><p>Ok, so now we know that as a general rule of thumb, shadows cast downward look more natural because our brains expect them to be obeying the Sun as the light source.</p><p>But how long should the shadow be cast, you ask? Well... looking back to our first law, that digital objects should obey physical rules: how high is it?</p><h2 id="cast-your-shadows-depending-on-the-elements-elevation">Cast your shadows depending on the element&apos;s &quot;elevation&quot;</h2><p><a href="https://m1.material.io/material-design/elevation-shadows.html?ref=theuilab.co">Google&apos;s Material design system does a pretty good job of explaining this.</a> Basically, if something is higher up, it should have a drop shadow that mimics the natural relationship of a light source and depth:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-shadow-depth-2.png" class="kg-image" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow" loading="lazy" width="829" height="437" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-shadow-depth-2.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-shadow-depth-2.png 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Notice how the shadow changes the closer it gets to a background surface.</figcaption></figure><p>How this relates to objects in our UIs is that we can use drop shadows to indicate to a user what depth certain elements are.</p><p>Elevated UI elements&apos; shadows should follow the same behavior and play against a backdrop the same as a physical object&apos;s would:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-shadow-depth-ui-1.png" class="kg-image" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow" loading="lazy" width="829" height="437" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-shadow-depth-ui-1.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-shadow-depth-ui-1.png 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>The higher the object is from the surface (aka, your screen,) the more diffuse the shadow will be.</p><p>Keep in mind that when you&apos;re designing a UI, you don&apos;t want to arbitrarily change the depth of shadows on your elements. This adds unnecessary complexity which will result in a bad experience for your users. </p><p>Instead, create and follow a system. What elements should have shadows (ie, which elements benefit from looking elevated?) and what height should they be? And then stick to that.</p><p>So, how else can we make those shadows more natural looking?</p><h2 id="combine-two-shadows-to-create-a-natural-shadow">Combine <em>two</em> shadows to create a natural shadow</h2><p>If you think of the shadows objects cast in real life, they appear to be pretty simple. Depending on the depth, they diffuse out from the &quot;edge&quot; of the object:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-natural-shadow-structure.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow" loading="lazy" width="829" height="425" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-natural-shadow-structure.jpg 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-natural-shadow-structure.jpg 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>However, when you look closer, on some shadows you&apos;ll find that it&apos;s possible to identify what look almost like separate &quot;layers&quot; or zones of density:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-natural-shadow-structure-outline.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow" loading="lazy" width="829" height="425" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-natural-shadow-structure-outline.jpg 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-natural-shadow-structure-outline.jpg 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>The thing is, like most things in real life, shadows are rarely perfectly defined or symmetrical. </p><p>And if we want to create more natural-looking, polished, and professional shadows in our UI designs, we should strive to more closely mimic the way shadows look in the natural world.</p><p>However, design tools as well as implementation are limited in the way they can produce shadows. Computers operate on deterministic principles. In the future, we may be able to more reliably (and more importantly: more efficiently) deterministically create less deterministic looking shadows. </p><div class="kg-card kg-callout-card kg-callout-card-grey"><div class="kg-callout-emoji">&#x1F914;</div><div class="kg-callout-text"><strong>Food for thought:</strong> The &quot;natural&quot; shadows in the real world are actually also truly deterministic; they only look organic because the variables present in the physical world are immensely more complex than what we can efficiently render with computers.</div></div><p><strong>For now, we&apos;ll have to settle for simulating it.</strong></p><p>To do so, we&apos;ll combine two shadows: <strong>a sharper, more dense shadow, and a larger, more diffuse one.</strong></p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-combined-shadows-3.png" class="kg-image" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow" loading="lazy" width="829" height="334" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-combined-shadows-3.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-combined-shadows-3.png 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Bam! We&apos;ve got a more natural shadow.</p><p>So here&apos;s how I did it:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-combined-shadows-settings.png" class="kg-image" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow" loading="lazy" width="829" height="587" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-combined-shadows-settings.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-combined-shadows-settings.png 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>You&apos;ll have to play with the settings to match your use case and background color, but it should give you a sense of how the two are combined.</p><p>And that leads me to the final step to creating more natural drop shadows in Figma...</p><h2 id="pro-tip-shadows-arent-black">Pro tip: Shadows aren&apos;t black</h2><p>You&apos;ve been lied to, folks. When we go to add a drop shadow to our UI element, this is what we get:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/basic-dropshadow.png" class="kg-image" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow" loading="lazy" width="998" height="548" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/basic-dropshadow.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/basic-dropshadow.png 998w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>If we&apos;re aiming to create the most polished, natural-looking shadows we can create, this a problem.</p><p><strong>If you didn&apos;t know this: shadows are not the color black on top of a background &#x2013; they are actually just the background, <em>with less light.</em></strong></p><p>Aka, shadows, <em>simplistically</em>, are just a <em>shade</em> of the background color. See? Even the words make sense now. Shade. Shadow.</p><p>The more complex answer is that the <em>true</em> color of a shadow is a combination of the color of the material it&apos;s cast onto, as well as the color of the reflection of any nearby objects, including the object that cast the shadow.</p><p><strong>Take a look around you and start noticing the true color of shadows on objects</strong>. For example, that shadow from earlier? Not black, or even gray. </p><p>It&apos;s like, totally blue:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-natural-shadow-true-color-blue.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow" loading="lazy" width="829" height="389" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-natural-shadow-true-color-blue.jpg 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-natural-shadow-true-color-blue.jpg 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>In context:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-true-shadow-colors.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow" loading="lazy" width="829" height="587" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-true-shadow-colors.jpg 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-true-shadow-colors.jpg 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Let&apos;s take a look at another example. See the shadow under this plant? </p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-true-shadow-colors-1.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow" loading="lazy" width="829" height="587" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-true-shadow-colors-1.jpg 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-true-shadow-colors-1.jpg 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>It&apos;s also not gray or anything like that. It&apos;s actually <em>brown</em>, because the wood underneath is brown, and there&apos;s just... less light getting to it. So it&apos;s just a shade of the color brown of the wood to the left of it.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-natural-true-shadow-royalbrown.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow" loading="lazy" width="829" height="389" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-natural-true-shadow-royalbrown.jpg 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-natural-true-shadow-royalbrown.jpg 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Pretty neat. The closer you look, the more colorful the world starts to seem.</p><p>That&apos;s why in this example from earlier, the shadow isn&apos;t black or gray, but is actually a dark blue:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/shadow-blue.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow" loading="lazy" width="829" height="235" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/shadow-blue.jpg 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/shadow-blue.jpg 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>And if we try the same thing with black or gray shadows, the result is less compelling:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/black-shadow.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="How to Create a Polished and Professional Figma Dropshadow" loading="lazy" width="829" height="235" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/black-shadow.jpg 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/black-shadow.jpg 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>And all of this is, once again, because of the first law of natural UI design:</p><blockquote>#1. Treat digital elements as if they exist in the physical world</blockquote><div class="kg-card kg-callout-card kg-callout-card-yellow"><div class="kg-callout-emoji">&#x1F914;</div><div class="kg-callout-text">Colors in UI shadows should be used carefully. Until recently, it wasn&apos;t something that could actually be implemented well on any platform. And done with a heavy hand, you can have some really... awful looking UIs. For the most part, I&apos;d only recommend using color-based shadows for <em>very </em>custom projects or UI-based illustrations. (think: Dribbble)</div></div><p></p><p>As always, thanks for reading, and please let me know if I left anything out OR could&apos;ve explained something better!</p><p>Happy designing!</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How to Use the Eyedropper Tool in Figma]]></title><description><![CDATA[Speed up your workflow by learning how to use the Eyedropper tool like a pro.]]></description><link>https://www.theuilab.co/use-the-eyedropper-tool/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">63599f6fc97b71003d4dcf9a</guid><category><![CDATA[Figma]]></category><category><![CDATA[Color]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gareth]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 21:17:47 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/eyedropper-figma-1.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/eyedropper-figma-1.png" alt="How to Use the Eyedropper Tool in Figma"><p>If you want to quickly pick the color from an image or a shape on the canvas, use the eyedropper tool. </p><p>It looks like this:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/eyedropper-1.png" class="kg-image" alt="How to Use the Eyedropper Tool in Figma" loading="lazy" width="829" height="437" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/eyedropper-1.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/eyedropper-1.png 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>In Figma, you can press &quot;i&quot; on the keyboard to select the Eyedropper. </p><p>Once it&apos;s selected, hover over an image or a shape on the canvas and click to sample the color. This will populate the color into the color picker.</p><p>If you first select a shape you want to change the color of, clicking to sample the color with the eyedropper tool will shape the color of the selected shape:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/fill-selected-shape-eyedropper.gif" class="kg-image" alt="How to Use the Eyedropper Tool in Figma" loading="lazy" width="600" height="328" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/fill-selected-shape-eyedropper.gif 600w"><figcaption>Select a shape, press &quot;i&quot;, then pick a color.</figcaption></figure><p><strong>Pro tip:</strong> We can take this further and &quot;scrub&quot; or continuously sample the image with the Eyedropper by clicking and dragging it across the image, trying different colors in context to feel out which one we like:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/continuously-sample-while-filling-shape.gif" class="kg-image" alt="How to Use the Eyedropper Tool in Figma" loading="lazy" width="600" height="328" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/continuously-sample-while-filling-shape.gif 600w"></figure><p>Neato, huh?</p><p><strong>Now let&apos;s take a look at a more advanced timesaving use-case. </strong></p><p>If we use the <strong>Selected Colors panel</strong> in Figma in conjunction with the continuous sampling using the Eyedropper tool, we can save a ton of time changing the color across a lot of elements:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/scrub-to-change-app-colors.gif" class="kg-image" alt="How to Use the Eyedropper Tool in Figma" loading="lazy" width="800" height="440" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/scrub-to-change-app-colors.gif 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/scrub-to-change-app-colors.gif 800w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><div class="kg-card kg-callout-card kg-callout-card-green"><div class="kg-callout-emoji">&#x1F4A1;</div><div class="kg-callout-text"><strong>Hint:</strong> this time saving feature gets wild when you start using Libraries (design systems in Figma.) Imagine changing the brand color of an entire 500-page website in 5 seconds. Figma is mind-blowing.</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How to Increase Contrast for Accessibility While Staying On-Brand]]></title><description><![CDATA[Simple tips and tricks to creating higher contrast within your brand color palette.]]></description><link>https://www.theuilab.co/make-elements-more-readable/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">63599f42c97b71003d4dcf90</guid><category><![CDATA[Accessibility]]></category><category><![CDATA[Color]]></category><category><![CDATA[Figma]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gareth]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 21:06:43 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/Contrast-3.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2></h2><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/Contrast-3.png" alt="How to Increase Contrast for Accessibility While Staying On-Brand"><p>This is my fianc&#xE9;&apos;s website, <a href="https://www.thegiggal.com/?ref=theuilab.co">The Gig Gal</a>. It has sort of a strawberry lemonade color scheme. The primary brand color is a salmon pink, and she typically applies it as accent colors throughout the website:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/thegiggal.com.png" class="kg-image" alt="How to Increase Contrast for Accessibility While Staying On-Brand" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="1571" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/thegiggal.com.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/thegiggal.com.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1600/2022/10/thegiggal.com.png 1600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/thegiggal.com.png 2342w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>The salmon color works well in larger area. However, when you use the brand color for links at small to normal sizes, the contrast is much too low:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/low-contrast-color.png" class="kg-image" alt="How to Increase Contrast for Accessibility While Staying On-Brand" loading="lazy" width="829" height="360" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/low-contrast-color.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/low-contrast-color.png 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Even though the two are literally the same color, when used in a small format, the brand color will look lighter and results in link text that is difficult to read.</p><p>If we run it through a WCAG-compliant contrast checker, we can see that it fails all accessibility standards for normal text:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/Screen-Shot-2022-10-26-at-12.41.33-PM.png" class="kg-image" alt="How to Increase Contrast for Accessibility While Staying On-Brand" loading="lazy" width="1446" height="868" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/Screen-Shot-2022-10-26-at-12.41.33-PM.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/Screen-Shot-2022-10-26-at-12.41.33-PM.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/Screen-Shot-2022-10-26-at-12.41.33-PM.png 1446w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Not so good! We need to up that contrast, but we need it to still feel like the Gig Gal branding.</p><p><strong>So, we can increase the contrast and make links more readable by:</strong></p><ol><li><strong> </strong>Increasing the saturation and/or the shade of the text color</li><li>Decreasing the saturation and increasing the tint of the background color</li></ol><p>Done together, looks like this:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/changes-to-value-and-saturation.png" class="kg-image" alt="How to Increase Contrast for Accessibility While Staying On-Brand" loading="lazy" width="829" height="437" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/changes-to-value-and-saturation.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/changes-to-value-and-saturation.png 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Darken and saturate foreground elements to increase contrast with light background colors.</figcaption></figure><p>Now let&apos;s try it out. How does it look? Is the link easier to see and read?</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/improve-contrast.png" class="kg-image" alt="How to Increase Contrast for Accessibility While Staying On-Brand" loading="lazy" width="880" height="893" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/improve-contrast.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/improve-contrast.png 880w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Okay, it seems easier to read. On the branding side, we took a small hit: maybe it feels a <em>little </em>less aligned to the brand. (this is just one reason why companies spend millions on rebrands. And most of them aren&apos;t as robust as they should be.) Alas, refining your color palette is a much more complex topic, and one that I will address in another article. </p><p><strong>For now, we want to use our color picker know-how increase contrast.</strong></p><p>So with that in mind: how well does the new link color do according to WCAG guidelines? Using the same WebAIM contrast checker, let&apos;s run it through again:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/wcag-pass-1.png" class="kg-image" alt="How to Increase Contrast for Accessibility While Staying On-Brand" loading="lazy" width="1446" height="830" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/wcag-pass-1.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/wcag-pass-1.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/wcag-pass-1.png 1446w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p><strong>Great success!</strong> We found a color that is based on the brand color that fully complies to minimum WCAG accessibility guidelines.</p><p>Now that we know the basics of how to use the color picker, let&apos;s get acquainted with some hot tips I&apos;ve picked up.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How To Use the Figma Color Picker]]></title><description><![CDATA[No need to keep guessing  there's a system behind it, and you can learn it.]]></description><link>https://www.theuilab.co/how-to-use-the-figma-color-picker/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6356f3118d8ceb003d7d5c22</guid><category><![CDATA[Figma]]></category><category><![CDATA[Color]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gareth]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 20:04:29 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/color-picker.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/11/color-picker.png" alt="How To Use the Figma Color Picker"><p>The color picker is an underrated and powerful tool for doing UI design in Figma. I&#x2019;ve been using it in my design workflow since I started doing design back in 2012. In fact, I honestly don&apos;t see a way that you can avoid using it. But for much of my time as a designer, I didn&#x2019;t really understand <em>how</em> it worked. &#xA0;It always kind of reminded me of one of these:<br></p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/gif-opt.gif" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use the Figma Color Picker" loading="lazy" width="250" height="274"><figcaption>Although fun, it&apos;s not particularly useful.</figcaption></figure><p>Like, hey, let&apos;s just sort of feel around a bit until we get something we like. I understood the basics, like moving the color slider around, and the fact that that the more you move it toward one color (from red to orange, for example), the more of that color would start to blend into the color you already had selected.</p><p>But at some point, I got frustrated by feeling like I wasn&apos;t really <em>getting </em>it. I felt like there had<em> </em>to be more to it. Was everyone<em> </em>using it like an ouija board like I was, sitting semi-aimlessly, hopelessly trying to summon the color spirits?<br></p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/13d585854801e879b7f3620e86ac961d.gif" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use the Figma Color Picker" loading="lazy" width="500" height="326"><figcaption>Casper the unfriendly ghost.</figcaption></figure><p>Turns out, like most things that seem like magic, there is more to the color picker than meets the eye. And by learning the basic mechanics of how it worked, I realized that I could start to reproducibly choose colors and accomplish what I was trying to accomplish both faster <em>and </em>more accurately. As you might imagine, that sped up my workflow by&#x2026; well, a bunch.</p><p>Using the color picker like a pro is a great boost to your productivity in Figma, as well as your confidence in your UI design ability. And it&#x2019;s not actually that complicated &#x2013; you only have to learn how it works once.</p><p>By the end of this short workshop, you&#x2019;ll be feeling confident in your Figma color picking abilities. You&#x2019;ll know how the color picker works, some pro tips on how to speed up your workflow, and the single most powerful thing you can practice to noticeably improve your color intuition.</p><p>So buckle up, because here&apos;s all you really need to know:</p><h2 id="hue-is-controlled-by-the-multi-colored-slider">Hue is controlled by the multi-colored slider</h2><p><strong>Your hue is the most basic version of the color you want to create.</strong> It&apos;s controlled by the rainbow road lookin&apos; slider at the bottom of the picker:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/hue-5.png" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use the Figma Color Picker" loading="lazy" width="829" height="693" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/hue-5.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/hue-5.png 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>This is the hue slider.</figcaption></figure><p>Playing around with the hue slider is <em>fun</em>. Everything changes color all at once, and I hope I&apos;m not alone when it starts to feel like you&apos;re back in Mario Kart 64 cruising down Rainbow Road. I like imagining that this is what you and I look like now, playing with our hue sliders together:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/tumblr_nwdo0xc5H11s3uawvo1_500.gif" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use the Figma Color Picker" loading="lazy" width="420" height="329"><figcaption>Maybe I could have rephrased that</figcaption></figure><h2 id="choose-the-saturation-of-a-color-by-moving-the-selector-left-and-right">Choose the saturation of a color by moving the selector <em>left and right</em></h2><p>You can think of saturation as the richness, or intensity, of the hue you selected. Notice how when we increase the saturation, the resulting color has a lot of the same characteristics as our previous color. It&apos;s just more rich, deep, and intense:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/less-saturated.png" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use the Figma Color Picker" loading="lazy" width="829" height="693" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/less-saturated.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/less-saturated.png 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Decrease the saturation by sliding the selector to the right. Left = less saturation, right = more saturation.</figcaption></figure><p></p><h2 id="change-how-light-or-dark-a-color-is-by-moving-the-selector-up-and-down">Change how light or dark a color is by moving the selector <em>up and down</em></h2><p><strong>This is called changing value. </strong>A change in value is to make the color more light (tint) or more dark (shade.)</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/more-dark-1.png" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use the Figma Color Picker" loading="lazy" width="829" height="693" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/more-dark-1.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/more-dark-1.png 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>If you want to learn more about hue, saturation, and value, <a href="https://www.theuilab.co/the-ui-designers-guide-to-color-2022/">check out the article I wrote here</a>.</p><h2 id="so-why-is-this-all-useful">So... why is this all useful?</h2><p>Well let me tell you, smartypants.</p><p><strong>When you understand the <em>system, </em>you can more effectively reproduce the results you&apos;re looking for.</strong></p><p>Imagine for example that you&apos;re trying to drive a newly-designed car. And for whatever reason, the makers of this horrible car decided that it only has one input: one giant stick in the middle that controls the car&apos;s direction <em>and</em> speed. </p><p>Without knowing the system behind it, you&apos;d just be sort of <em>feeling in the dark </em>for<em> </em>the perfect diagonal combination of controls to match the speed and direction of cars around you:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/trying-to-match-speed-1.png" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use the Figma Color Picker" loading="lazy" width="1048" height="693" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/trying-to-match-speed-1.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/trying-to-match-speed-1.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/trying-to-match-speed-1.png 1048w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Using the color selector without knowing the controls is kinda like driving this stupid car. But less dangerous.</figcaption></figure><p><strong>This is basically the ouija-board-plasma-ball-color-picker version of driving this car.</strong></p><p>You might gradually build some sort of intuition over time. But life is hard enough as it is, and most of the time you&apos;re just trying to get from point A to point B. So you don&apos;t spend much of your energy internalizing what&apos;s going on, and next time you get in the car it&apos;s like starting all over again.</p><p>But then you learn how the car really works.</p><p>If you push the stick one way, the car will go forward. If you push it another way, it will go backward. Moving the stick left and right changes the speed. </p><p><strong>Say it looks something like this:</strong></p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/weird-car.png" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use the Figma Color Picker" loading="lazy" width="1048" height="693" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/weird-car.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/weird-car.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/weird-car.png 1048w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Please, no one invent this car.</figcaption></figure><p>In this case it&apos;s still a pretty stupid design, but now you know <em>how</em> it works, and in the future you&apos;ll be able to use it more effectively and more consistently.</p><p>Which leads me to my main point...</p><h2 id="understanding-the-color-picker-helps-you-be-a-more-effective-designer">Understanding the color picker helps you be a more effective designer</h2><p>The system for controlling the color picker is the standard for the moment.</p><p>While not as silly as the imaginary car example, it is still completely <em>invisible</em> to you as a user.</p><p><strong>Learning how the Figma color picker works comes in <u>super</u> handy when you&apos;re creating color palettes or trying to find colors that feel like they live in the same universe as each other. </strong></p><p>Ok, I know that might all sound<em> </em>good, if not a little confusing, so let&apos;s look at an example.</p><p>We&apos;ll make sort of a proto-color-palette out of the color we had from the hue, saturation, and value examples. We&apos;re not going to go super deep right now into creating color palettes,<strong> for now we just want a reliable way to find different colors that look like they live in the same world.</strong></p><p>So we liked the kinda pastel dark blue:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/color-2.png" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use the Figma Color Picker" loading="lazy" width="829" height="693" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/color-2.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/color-2.png 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Now, let&apos;s find a <em>similar </em>color based on a totally different hue. We want it to stay just as dark/light and just as saturated to keep that dark pastel color.</p><p>All we do is move the hue slider:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/same-values--different-hue-2-2.png" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use the Figma Color Picker" loading="lazy" width="829" height="693" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/same-values--different-hue-2-2.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/same-values--different-hue-2-2.png 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>So now we have these two colors:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/similar-colors-based-on-hue.png" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use the Figma Color Picker" loading="lazy" width="829" height="437" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/similar-colors-based-on-hue.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/similar-colors-based-on-hue.png 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Do we like them? A little too... gentle? Need more contrast? Let&apos;s do it.</p><p>We can increase contrast against lighter background colors by increasing saturation or darkness. So, let&apos;s just make these same colors a little more saturated. </p><p>To do this, we&apos;ll just move the colorspace selector for each to the right:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/same-hues-and-value-more-saturation.png" class="kg-image" alt="How To Use the Figma Color Picker" loading="lazy" width="829" height="693" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/same-hues-and-value-more-saturation.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/same-hues-and-value-more-saturation.png 829w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>More saturation, more fun.</figcaption></figure><p>So now we&apos;ve taken the colors we liked, made them more saturated, all the while keeping them at the same level of darkness (value).</p><p>Next, we&apos;ll learn how to use this in a real world situation.</p><h2></h2><h2></h2>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The UI Designer's Guide to Color: 2022]]></title><description><![CDATA[Color is a high-leverage tool you can use to make your UI designs more beautiful and useful. Learn to master what colors to use for UI design.]]></description><link>https://www.theuilab.co/the-ui-designers-guide-to-color-2022/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">634dd9bbcde2f3004d9d24fc</guid><category><![CDATA[Color]]></category><category><![CDATA[Visual Design]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gareth]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 20:27:08 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-color-header-masters-3.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-color-header-masters-3.png" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022"><p><br>When I was starting my UI design journey, the topic of color gave me anxiety. It felt like people who were good at using color were tapping into some sort of unicorn blood-fueled black magic, and that no matter how hard I tried, I&#x2019;d never be able to do what they did. And for context, I was feeling this way <em>with a graphic design background</em>! </p><p>Truthfully, using color in user interfaces does require some specific knowledge, but it&#x2019;s far from black magic. I wish I had someone to sit down with me and tell me what I <em>actually </em>need to know, because all I had at the time was my own anxiety and a handful of &#x201C;designery&#x201D; articles about color theory and the golden ratio.</p><p>The truth is, like all skills in life, it&#x2019;s not hard to do, you just have to learn it. And if I can learn it, you can learn it &#x2014; and neither of us even has to hunt a unicorn to do it. And I&#x2019;ll do you one even better: once it starts to click, it can be <em>fun</em>.</p><p>Let me caveat here for a second: I&#x2019;m not going to go super deep into color theory or get too theoretical. This article is meant to be <em>practical</em>, not exhaustive. It&#x2019;s my hope that by the end of this article, you&#x2019;ll feel more confident to start experimenting with color yourself.</p><p><strong>I&#x2019;ll cover things like:</strong></p><ul><li><strong><strong><strong>How important color is for UI design</strong></strong></strong></li><li><strong><strong><strong>What colors to use in your UI and when</strong></strong></strong></li><li><strong><strong><strong>How many colors you should use when designing a UI</strong></strong></strong></li><li><strong><strong><strong>How to know if your UI color choices look good</strong></strong></strong></li></ul><p>And I&#x2019;ll include examples to help you actually see some of this stuff in action. But quickly before I go into that, I want you to keep something in mind:</p><h2 id="color-is-surprisingly-flexible">Color is surprisingly flexible</h2><p>When I went to design school, I learned that you generally want to avoid colors that clash or create a sense of vibration (for example, light blues and oranges.) But let&#x2019;s take a moment to a look at this crazy use of color:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/wje0NaVKIuK7HvlZ76hi4NGPQjmbVnXY5Q3rkqwD06M0Yu04l3DVnd6ZRWYdSgnq91WLrMV_SYAdyKA_pU_DoFoVTCyHKuJAIubWNaPMHgzL6OfjDaJvdhNRIaoOhG5pNy1AdqNasLCmH2IpTZQIkYHDSpBhynxTZx4QTlWzf0gVDPLPEYdcM0VKTw" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="624" height="432"></figure><p>The blue stripes inside the orange pants absolutely <em>shatter </em>the traditional take on what I learned about color. But somehow&#x2026; it works? Magic. For the moment, I want you to throw out everything you thought you knew about color. To learn color, you need to experiment.</p><p>It&#x2019;s important to keep in mind the context in which you&#x2019;re using color. This example is an illustration, and therefore it has a different ruleset. When you use color in your UI designs, you want to use color more precisely. And whereas our friend Sebastian here probably actually <em>intended </em>to create a muddy/vibrant effect, we do not necessarily want our button text to feel that way; we want ours to be readable. <strong>Main point here? Color is weird</strong>. And cool.</p><h2 id="how-important-is-color-to-ui-design"><strong>How important is color to UI design?</strong></h2><p>Let me just be super straightforward here to dispel a myth, and hopefully save you some time: <strong>color impacts our emotions</strong>. You can fast-forward through the debate about whether color theory &#x201C;works&#x201D; or not. It&apos;s for real, I&apos;m just going to tell you now.</p><p>Some associations we have with color are certainly socialized as opposed to innate. For example, there&#x2019;s no reason for example to think the color blue &#x1F499;<em> </em>is associated with <em>trust </em>other than the fact that a million financial institutions use it.</p><p></p><p>And even that may be because of more innate associations like the calming effect of water or the sky when you&#x2019;re interacting with a survival-related and stress-laden topic such as money. Food for another day&apos;s thought, I suppose.</p><p>I would argue that whether or not any particular color association is innate or socialized doesn&#x2019;t matter. All that matters is if we have them or not, and the answer to that question is a just plain <strong>yes we do</strong>.</p><p>But let&apos;s take a quick bus ride over to an example. Think about the last time you tried a delicious new food. What did it look like?</p><p>Maybe something like this:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/qOwSvluG80qI1WXoOlpOmUAqO5yvq7yzGOxnFfHWXwuu6_ZR-VvNhs3d1S8T4QLd8SY7wTTj_lFHpEpOa7WLZRWUGBtccATOak5QHF4bgk_KCB6FgB9Q2naV3bS5czTFL9Qj6_dRH3veREGNiIvNS5Y_0WPwAJOnRDDGFx1PZw6OGC-H80iMwc0aqA" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="624" height="509"></figure><p>Or this:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/WiLaGND9j5pmpcRqhsqeevQZgOzA7CCG3ZWrtkSJjs3UtWICPYicRNUn9Q1JlinirgqdF5I1nvGRkx1dlqsgC9QGPwJGtmM4bVTKSCJO5kIUXIKH-OR_qi_LHZgWI-KcwQktrw09tmSP597ysquYqRkLeGYH-mP4HaDm71-FbYkUsUu3mFP5tOTMuQ" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="624" height="509"></figure><p>&#x2026;. No?</p><p>Ok, maybe that first one was a little more like this:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/PHpJG90ncu-QxcEnFQfnaSrQ3duk-NiXdbgKcM7VAtfPCEWwsaeDXQW4kZmTjc-OwXV_dLNrBCwhQJ_GjMLHJOX9AbWg4gFOeeEXGt0IOe7rRgFMV93XWXnmpGC2cYksOaAt0N86IWPEcgVtymadtxxeR_mEqTk8DS9PeEDDqSInOs59I514-tEFfw" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="624" height="509"></figure><p>Or this!</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/E0ZCdW_obSrYZNnQ-dQrBBBm435Kuuk1VPhBJbw6v6ipKEU_X6AngEfTGT7iNjZS2LMasnRlVPXrVRT6PNXy97T8bp17AXPJghIna0bQEnYZOplBAWtBUVivsdW4GMlum8CCW6HmSfc8EMV7-23dWCZZX7IKssHxD-19a69NDDP--X9G84_gn98eug" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="624" height="509"></figure><p>Alright, alright. Pretty on the nose, you say.</p><p><strong>But here&apos;s the thing:</strong> pay attention to how you<em> feel </em>when you look at the black and white version, and then, when you look at the version with color. Especially if you&#x2019;re hungry. <strong>Maybe this even </strong><em><strong>made</strong></em><strong> you hungry. </strong>(sorry!)</p><p>Now, take a look back at the first image. At a glance, how easy is it for you to identify the different components of the bowl without color? With color?</p><p>When designers talk about &#x201C;CoLoR tHeOrY,&#x201D; it sometimes feels like a very lofty, academic, and pretentious topic. Maybe it even feels a little ... I don&apos;t know, made up?</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/z63507a90d6085.gif" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="803" height="200" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/z63507a90d6085.gif 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/z63507a90d6085.gif 803w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p><strong>But our food example here is the practical version of what that&#x2019;s all about.</strong> We all know color is important. Maybe we just haven&#x2019;t thought about <em>how </em>important it is, or maybe it feels like UI design is some other, detached world from the world of tex-mex bowls and steaks, but it&#x2019;s actually one in the same.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-confusing-alert-1.png" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="1600" height="1100" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-confusing-alert-1.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/uilab-confusing-alert-1.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-confusing-alert-1.png 1600w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>A great way to confuse your users</figcaption></figure><p><strong>At its core, color is just a high-bandwidth vehicle for information,</strong> both emotional and functional. It shortcuts the conscious part of your brain and taps right into the deeper subconscious part, very quickly telling us what&apos;s up without us even knowing it.</p><p>And <strong>if color is an information vehicle, and design is the science of visual communication, then color is a fundamental pillar of that science. </strong></p><p><strong>Aka, color is important as heck in UI. </strong>And it&#x2019;s worth learning!</p><p>Ok. Enough on that. Still with me?</p><p>When you&#x2019;re trying to up your UI design color game, you really only need to know a few basic principles to start being a capable colorer.</p><p>First, let&#x2019;s take a <em>brief </em>tour of color theory.</p><h2 id="color-theory-is-kinda-simple"><strong>Color theory is kinda simple</strong></h2><p><strong>Every single color that we see is a result of a combination of 3 colors:</strong> &#xA0;red &#x1F534;, green &#x1F7E2;, and blue &#x1F535;. &#xA0;These are called <strong>primary</strong> colors of light, and they are legit:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/primary-colors-1.png" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="1600" height="1100" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/primary-colors-1.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/primary-colors-1.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/primary-colors-1.png 1600w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>And by &quot;every color we see,&quot; I mean <em><strong>everything</strong></em>. The color of the leaves on the trees outside, your favorite plum colored sweater, the pukey-poopy upholstered furniture set&#x2026; all of it. <strong>Imagine everything you see in terms of the intensity of each of the 3 primary colors.</strong></p><p>For example, the <strong>leaves on the tree</strong> might be something like:</p><p>Red: 50% Green: 62% Blue: 25%</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilabco-tree-color-composition.gif" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="600" height="412" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilabco-tree-color-composition.gif 600w"></figure><p>And<strong> your favorite plum sweater</strong> might be:</p><p>Red: 37% Green: 31% Blue: 46%</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilabco-plum-color-composition.gif" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="600" height="412" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilabco-plum-color-composition.gif 600w"></figure><p>And <strong>grandma&#x2019;s furniture</strong> might be:</p><p>Red: 72% Green: 53% Blue: 38%</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilabco-couch-color-composition.gif" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="600" height="412" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilabco-couch-color-composition.gif 600w"></figure><p><strong>I would highly, highly, highly recommend you try this: </strong></p><ol><li>Go outside</li><li>Find an object with a color you want to guess</li><li>Guess what percentages of color might make it up</li></ol><p>Practicing this is a way to make meaningful progress <strong>today</strong>.</p><p>Even just going out and doing this once a day on a walk, or when you&#x2019;re picking up groceries after work, is a very real way that you can start to build your color intuition. You&apos;ll start <em>noticing </em>color more.</p><p>And even better than that, <strong>the more you do this, the more you will close the gap between your ability to imagine how something should look, and your ability to create something that looks like how you imagine it.</strong></p><p>You should also know: there are also such things as secondary and tertiary colors, and I would recommend reading up on those just so you know what they are. Secondary colors are two primary colors combined, and tertiary are the combination of a primary and secondary. </p><p>And heck, here&#x2019;s a color wheel so you can see:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/BYR_color_wheel.svg" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy"><figcaption>A common color wheel. Pretty.</figcaption></figure><p>Otherwise, for the sake of this article and for your time, I won&#x2019;t go into those any further. There are a million articles and a Wikipedia page that will do a way better job if you&#x2019;re interested!</p><p>However, I wouldn&#x2019;t worry too much about secondary and tertiary colors or the color wheel for now.</p><p>You&#x2019;ll reference them occasionally over time, but for our purposes, we&#x2019;ll focus on something else:</p><h2 id="the-color-picker">The Color Picker</h2><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/color-picker-1.png" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="1600" height="1100" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/color-picker-1.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/color-picker-1.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/color-picker-1.png 1600w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Learn this tool. Once you get it, this tool will be your best friend.</p><p><strong>It&#x2019;s also pretty easy, once you understand how it works:</strong></p><h3 id="hue"><strong>Hue</strong></h3><p><strong>Hue is the purest version of the color itself.</strong> It&#x2019;s the mostest reddest red, and the mostest bluest blue, and so on. Primary, secondary, tertiary colors and everything in between are all hues. You control the hue by selecting a position on the rainbow bar on the bottom, and then moving the selector all the way to the top right of the bar.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/hue-1.png" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="1600" height="1100" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/hue-1.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/hue-1.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/hue-1.png 1600w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><h3 id="value"><strong>Value</strong></h3><p><strong>Value is the amount of black (shade) or white (tint) mixed with the color.</strong> You change the value by sliding up or down. Changing this changes &#x2026; well, the darkness or the lightness of the color.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/value-1.png" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="1600" height="1100" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/value-1.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/value-1.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/value-1.png 1600w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><h3 id="saturation"><strong>Saturation</strong></h3><p><strong>Saturation is the intensity of the color.</strong> Aka, how much <em>hue</em> the color has. Change this by sliding left and right.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/saturation-1.png" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="1600" height="1100" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/saturation-1.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/saturation-1.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/saturation-1.png 1600w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>And that&#x2019;s literally all there is to it. You can make every single visible color by adjusting these 3 properties. And from there, it&#x2019;s just a matter of practicing using it and building your color muscle.</p><p>Now knowing how to use the picker, start practicing your color-recreating abilities, but this time using a photo and the color picker. <strong>Try to recreate the color you see simply by changing the hue, saturation, and value.</strong></p><p>You will get better at this the more you do it, I promise. </p><p><strong>Eventually you&#x2019;ll be nailing colors and people will be paying you to do it.</strong></p><p>So, we&#x2019;ve covered the basics of color and how to create the colors you want. Now you might be wondering&#x2026; okay, but what colors do I use, and when?</p><h2 id="what-colors-to-use-in-your-ui-and-when"><strong>What colors to use in your UI, and when</strong></h2><p>So here&#x2019;s the thing. We know color affects how we feel. But what colors mean what? And how do you know when or when not to use a color?</p><p><strong>First you need to know that some colors take priority over others.</strong> This is because they are used to communicate very important information.</p><p>Let&#x2019;s take red for example, stop signs are red because red communicates arrest, intensity, and danger. Check out this dangerous stuff:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/79bduhiQMDniCO88b8nNvNQkYfrxcIJlKWlyG9rhDH9jePVEcW1e54ibBfJzvcvP9pFDj7ZeZiNrDU14dqOih4GLBdwEwHPRiuN9DNrzbz4gei0YPlmhhSOqK-_AXauppuaWwaiqaR0KgIdgsbpk_7PqjxtAy5xOyYIT8jwmZnsedflI1u2wtcQT4w" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="624" height="429"></figure><p>That&#x2019;s not to say that everything that is red is dangerous. Tomatoes, for example, are a delicious red <em><strong>fruit </strong></em>(I said it) that are only dangerous when they&#x2019;re being hurdled at you in a tomato fight.</p><p><strong>But the effects some colors have on our psychology are distinct and pronounced, </strong>so you want to <em>try</em> to reserve them for very important use-cases. This isn&#x2019;t to say that you can&#x2019;t ever use red for anything else, though. Keep in mind that these are guidelines, and guidelines can be broken when the situation calls for it.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/N7IRNQ7tBgYsSS4I_MwansPhJ5WJXNIHSKxXbd4iS538Yzm0Iyel-UGOqHBlhEpN7yhZZ9dN8uA3UFPYJ1gWGv1DAGH3sLSkHsciba4o4erns8FmzUN7DhgYINim3GqJcDYkSg1GdDkK6XtHWpeQityO1aMD7my2nN2jO0tXDQeaWpEW_5sIE-btOw" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="498" height="331"></figure><p>So here&#x2019;s a quick guide on when to use certain colors. Again, this is a set of guidelines intended to help you get started as a beginner, and guidelines, are&#x2026; well, guidelines. Use them until you feel confident about which ones are okay breaking and when (you&#x2019;ll build this muscle over time.)</p><h2 id="red"><strong>Red</strong></h2><p><strong>Common UI elements:</strong> Errors, when things are broken, alerts, alarms, critical problems, sometimes offline status, stop, destructive actions (like a &#x201C;delete&#x201D; button)</p><p><strong>Emotion &amp; brand associations:</strong> Danger, aggression, anger, passion, love, danger, &#x201C;stop&#x201D; sentiment, richness</p><h2 id="orange"><strong>Orange</strong></h2><p><strong>Common UI elements: </strong>Medium-intensity alerts, something needs attention</p><p><strong>Emotion &amp; brand assocations:</strong> Excitement, warmth</p><p><strong>Avoid:</strong> similar to red</p><h2 id="yellow"><strong>Yellow</strong></h2><p><strong>Common UI elements</strong>: not many</p><p><strong>Emotion &amp; brand assocations:</strong> Happiness, warmth, sunshine, caution</p><p><strong>Avoid: </strong>similar to red and orange</p><h2 id="green"><strong>Green</strong></h2><p><strong>Common UI elements:</strong> Online/active/positive status, done-ness (think checkmarks,) good to go, positive signals</p><p><strong>Emotion &amp; brand associations:</strong> Environment, natural, positivity, &#x201C;go&#x201D; sentiment</p><h2 id="blue"><strong>Blue</strong></h2><p><strong>Common UI elements:</strong> Typically only branded UI elements (buttons, etc)</p><p><strong>Emotion &amp; brand associations:</strong> Trust, calm, &#x201C;all good&#x201D; ness, security</p><h2 id="purple"><strong>Purple</strong></h2><p><strong>UI elements:</strong> Typically only branded UI elements (buttons, etc)</p><p><strong>Emotion &amp; brand applications:</strong> Richness, royalty, magic</p><p>Now that you know some of these associations, start looking for them in the apps and websites you use, as well as stuff out in the real world. If you&#x2019;ve never touched on this before, it might blow your mind how much subtle signaling is happening on a daily basis.</p><p>Which leads me to one of the most important points I will make:</p><h2 id="you-should-limit-the-number-of-colors-you-use-in-your-ui-design"><strong>You should limit the number of colors you use in your UI design</strong></h2><p>Color is obviously an extremely useful tool in design. That being said, it&#x2019;s easy to get excited and overdo the number of colors you have. I&#x2019;ll be the first to say it: once you get the hang of it, color is <em>fun</em>. I <em>love </em>color. But there&#x2019;s a direct relationship to the number of colors your UI uses and the complexity of your UI.</p><p><strong>As a reminder: color is a vehicle that carries information.</strong></p><p><strong>Complexity isn&#x2019;t necessarily bad. </strong>It&#x2019;s a good thing your glass-top stove puts red outlines where the burners underneath are so that you don&#x2019;t burn your hands every gee-dang time you&#x2019;re trying to make a meal. The red lines add complexity, but it&#x2019;s also <em>useful </em>complexity.</p><p><strong>In UI design, too few colors can also be unhelpful. </strong>You don&#x2019;t want your &#x201C;Permanently Delete Forever&#x201D; button to look the same as your &#x201C;Sounds good&#x201D; button.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-confusingbuttons.gif" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="1200" height="825" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-confusingbuttons.gif 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/uilab-confusingbuttons.gif 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-confusingbuttons.gif 1200w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>In case it isn&apos;t clear... don&apos;t do this.</figcaption></figure><p>If it does, you may get people accidentally tapping it, deleting all their stuff, and getting rightfully frustrated at you for misleading them.</p><p>But too <em>many</em> colors is also unhelpful.</p><p><strong>As a rule of thumb, you want just enough color in your UI to carry the meanings you need. No more, no less.</strong></p><p>With that said, generally speaking, you&#x2019;ll need to consider <strong>4 basic colors</strong> when you&#x2019;re designing a new UI:</p><ol><li>Background color</li><li>Your primary, or main, color</li><li>Secondary, or accent, color</li><li>Semantic colors</li></ol><p>You may use variations within those colors, but you want to keep the total number of colors low.</p><p><strong>Also, just as a side note: primary and secondary colors in this context are not the same as primary and secondary colors on the color wheel.</strong> It just means your more important and less important color.</p><h3 id="1-background-color"><strong>1. Background color</strong></h3><p>Imagine you&#x2019;re painting the walls in your apartment or house. The background color is kinda like the base wall paint color you&#x2019;d choose for your interior walls. Its purpose is to serve as a backdrop for the stuff that goes on top or in front of it. Typically it&#x2019;s a neutral, white-based color, or a soft gray, and it&#x2019;s easy on the eyes.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-wallcolor.png" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="1600" height="1100" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-wallcolor.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/uilab-wallcolor.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-wallcolor.png 1600w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Notice how the wall color allows more dominant elements stand out. Bonus practice points: what order did you look at the objects in the room, and why? Color, size, shape, and depth all contribute to the hierarchy of the composition.</figcaption></figure><p>It should be neutral enough so that the things that will go on top of it (text, media like photos/illustrations, icons, buttons, and so on) have enough contrast to be easy to read, identify, and use. In this way, the background color you choose is actually the foundation for the visual hierarchy of your app or website.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-nike-bgcolor.png" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="1600" height="1100" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-nike-bgcolor.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/uilab-nike-bgcolor.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-nike-bgcolor.png 1600w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Can you easily identify the most important parts of the screen and where Nike thinks you should look? Thank you, neutral background color!</figcaption></figure><p><em>Although some of us may paint our walls in more fun ways, keep in mind that at the end of the day, user interfaces are tools, and people will actually be using what you&#x2019;re designing here. So it&#x2019;s important to be able to find things, read them, and use them, and therefore more important to use neutral colors for backgrounds. If you really love the color red, you might paint your dorm room red, but you wouldn&#x2019;t surround a red emergency SOS button in a red wall. Unless you&#x2019;re a horrible person.</em></p><p>It&#x2019;s best to stick with 1 background color, but feel free to include a variant or two. In certain circumstances, you may need 2 background colors. Imagine Google Docs, for example, where a light gray background creates definition for a white page, and then the white page creates definition for the content (text, photos.):</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-googledocs-bgcolor.png" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="1600" height="1100" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-googledocs-bgcolor.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/uilab-googledocs-bgcolor.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-googledocs-bgcolor.png 1600w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Google docs uses a light gray background color to outline the page, which then becomes the background for the written content.</figcaption></figure><h3 id="2-primary-color"><strong>2. Primary color</strong></h3><p>This is the color or colors you&#x2019;ll use for large areas of your UI. In most cases it is the primary color that is associated with your brand. For Coke, think red. It will often be used for things that are on top of and therefore surrounded by your background color, and may often contain text, so it should be clearly visible and high-contrast against your background color. Also consider how easy it is to read text that is inside it.</p><p>In some cases, your primary color will be used for large branded areas, such as a header, as well as buttons.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilabco-fitbit-primary-colors-2.png" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="1600" height="1100" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilabco-fitbit-primary-colors-2.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/uilabco-fitbit-primary-colors-2.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilabco-fitbit-primary-colors-2.png 1600w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Fitbit uses their primary color for dominant UI elements. Yes, I need to get more sleep.</figcaption></figure><p>In some cases the primary brand color will conflict with colors that should be reserved for important states, like error states. Or it may create readability issues when text is placed over it. </p><p>Say, for example, your brand color is a bright orange. In that case, you might consider using another color that pairs well with your brand color for things like buttons (for example, if your secondary brand color is a rich black color, use that) or a shade of your primary brand color (in the Coca Cola example, a dark red) to increase the visibility of text against the button. </p><p>Or, you can use your brand color as an accent color instead. As a <em>rule of thumb</em>, your primary color should be no more than ~30% of the visible UI on your screen at any given point in time.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-cocacola-primarycolor.png" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="1600" height="1100" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-cocacola-primarycolor.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/uilab-cocacola-primarycolor.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-cocacola-primarycolor.png 1600w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Coca Cola uses their primary brand color for most UI elements and accent colors.</figcaption></figure><h3 id="3-secondary-or-accent-colors"><strong>3. Secondary, or accent, color(s)</strong></h3><p>Your accent color is typically another brand color and is often used to call attention to a specific part of the UI. For example, your main call to action buttons might use your accent color. Or you might use it for linked text or icons. Generally speaking though, your accent color should account for roughly 10% of your color usage at most.</p><p>Here&apos;s an example of background, primary, and accent colors in action:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilabco-m1finance-colors.png" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="1600" height="1100" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilabco-m1finance-colors.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/uilabco-m1finance-colors.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilabco-m1finance-colors.png 1600w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>M1 Finance&apos;s color scheme is a bit more complex.</figcaption></figure><h3 id="4-semantic-colors"><strong>4. Semantic Colors</strong></h3><p>Semantic colors are colors you&#x2019;ll use for things like errors, warnings, notifications, deleting, and so on. These are purely functional in nature, and colors you&#x2019;ll want to reconcile with your color scheme at large.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilabco-semantic-colors.png" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="1600" height="1100" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilabco-semantic-colors.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/uilabco-semantic-colors.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilabco-semantic-colors.png 1600w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Now, all of this is only a guideline; over time you&#x2019;ll build a better sense of when and where you want to apply your color.</p><p>And I know what you might be thinking right now: wait a second, your primary color can be your brand color. But your accent color can also be your brand color? Which should I use for which?</p><p><strong>The cold hard facts: it&#x2019;s not a perfect science.</strong></p><p>Here&#x2019;s what I&#x2019;d recommend.</p><p>Start with a baseline of guidelines (60% background / 30% primary / 10% accent) and semantic colors (examples: errors = red,) and build on it over time. Each app and website is unique, and the more you practice using color, the more you&#x2019;ll build intuition of which color, how much to use, when, and where.</p><p>You may decide that you don&#x2019;t need a primary color in your design at all, and that you want your brand to come into play in the form of photos and accent colors. As with everything in UI design, context is important.</p><p>Nike is an excellent example of this: they made the decision to focus much of the visual attention on the photography of their shoes, since by nature, this is their &#x201C;product&#x201D;. The result? Most of their actual &#x201C;UI&#x201D; is white or light gray background. Their primary color is used for call to action buttons (aka Add to Cart) and they merely sprinkle in an orange accent color throughout the app:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-nike-primary-accent-1.png" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="1600" height="1100" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-nike-primary-accent-1.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/uilab-nike-primary-accent-1.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-nike-primary-accent-1.png 1600w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p><strong>At the end of the day, you need to do some of your own experimentation to get a sense for which colors to use where. </strong>Find examples of apps or websites you like, and copy them. Learn how many colors they&#x2019;re using, and see if you can find a pattern or a system.<br></p><h2 id="there-is-no-perfect-science-to-making-something-%E2%80%9Clook-good%E2%80%9D"><strong>There is no perfect science to making something &#x201C;look good&#x201D;</strong></h2><p>Unfortunately for those of us graced with the affliction of perfectionism, I&#x2019;m here to break it to you: you can&#x2019;t logic color past a certain point.</p><p><strong>The truth is, it&#x2019;s like learning a language.</strong></p><p>First, you learn the words. Get a sense for what words mean what, and when to use them. Then, you learn the rules. &#x201C;Never start a sentence with the word &#x2018;but&#x2019;,&#x201D; they say. &#x201C;But starting a sentence with &#x2018;but&#x2019; adds tonality to your writing!&#x201D; you say. See what I did there? You learn the rules, and then you learn how to break, or maybe more accurately, <em>bend</em> them.</p><p><strong>Unfortunately, there&#x2019;s no objective way to know if the colors you&#x2019;re using &#x201C;look good&#x201D;.</strong></p><p>You <em>can</em>, however, learn by paying attention to things that <em>you</em> think look good, observing how it&#x2019;s being done, and learning how to do it yourself.</p><p><strong>That being said, UI design is, first and foremost, about usability. </strong>Here&#x2019;s a practical checklist you can run through as you&#x2019;re working on something:</p><ol><li><strong>Can you read it</strong></li><li><strong>Can other people read it</strong></li><li><strong>Would the brand do it</strong></li><li><strong>Be kind to yourself</strong></li></ol><p>By running your designs through these checks, you can at least start to understand if your UI will be easy to read and use.</p><h3 id="1-can-you-read-it">1. Can YOU read it?</h3><p>Okay, so you came up with a color scheme, and you tried designing something with it. <strong>The first, fastest, most practical way to understand if your design works or not is a little closer to home than you think: yourself.</strong></p><p>You are, after all, a human being. That&#x2019;s all it takes to be a qualified user. So tap into your own user sensibilities, imagine you&#x2019;re not you&#x2026; and take a look.</p><p>What do you think? Is it easy to read? Is it easy to know what to do next? Do you know where to tap? If not: try to identify what&#x2019;s going wrong. Maybe one area looks right, and one doesn&#x2019;t.</p><p>There&#x2019;s no speed-running this process; it&#x2019;s how you have to learn.</p><p>Look at what you&#x2019;re doing, and look at examples of what others are doing where you don&#x2019;t get that prickly uncomfortable feeling. Compare them. Figure out what&#x2019;s different and try something else. Maybe it&#x2019;s a contrast issue. Maybe the colors just don&#x2019;t jive together.</p><h3 id="2-make-sure-other-people-can-read-it">2. Make sure other people can read it</h3><p>If you&#x2019;re not familiar with the topic, designing for accessibility is essentially the philosophy of designing things in a way that allows the maximum number of people to successfully use whatever you designed.</p><p>In UI design, this often plays out as making sure the contrast between certain elements in your design is high enough that is easy to read even for the most vision-impaired.</p><p><strong>Why&#x2019;s that a good idea? By designing something to be effective for those who would find it most difficult to use, we are putting maximum effort into designing it well</strong><em><strong>, period</strong></em><strong>.</strong> And if we can make life easier for more people, then we&#x2019;re doing our jobs well too.</p><p>A tool that you can use for this kind of accessibility checking is a contrast checker. There are many available, just be sure to use one that adheres to WCAG (<strong>Web Content Accessibility Guidelines).</strong></p><p><a href="https://webaim.org/resources/contrastchecker/?ref=theuilab.co">I like this one.</a></p><h3 id="3-do-things-that-make-sense-for-the-brand">3. Do things that make sense for the brand</h3><p>Coca Cola&#x2019;s not about to launch their main app with big green, purple and yellow banners and buttons.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-cocacola-bad-1.png" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="1600" height="1100" srcset="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/uilab-cocacola-bad-1.png 600w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/uilab-cocacola-bad-1.png 1000w, https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/uilab-cocacola-bad-1.png 1600w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>This won&apos;t happen until 2084</figcaption></figure><p>Branding is a much larger topic, but go back to the color associations drawing board and pull from there. Should people feel a sense of trust when they come into your app? Or do you want them to feel engaged and excited? How about calm and relaxed? Maybe like they&#x2019;re in a place of luxury? What colors can you lean into to match the the goal of your new &#x201C;brand&#x201D;?</p><p>There&#x2019;s a reason Tinder is fiery red, and why Apple is an austere white and black.</p><h3 id="4-don%E2%80%99t-stress-about-being-unique">4. Don&#x2019;t stress about being unique</h3><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/anchromanBigDeal.gif.webp" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="300" height="151"></figure><p>Honestly, this is such a hard thing as a designer. But the truth is, there are <em>so many people on this planet and like, so many of those people have had ideas and businesses and apps and websites.</em></p><p><strong>I will tell you now: it&#x2019;s all been done before.</strong> Every color scheme under the moon has been thought of. It&#x2019;s how well you use it to solve the problem, and the context you apply it in that will make it successful or not. </p><p>Mozart didn&#x2019;t bother himself with whether or not others had used notes in a certain order. Rather, he focused on telling the story he needed to tell through music, combining techniques created by others before him, and the result ended up being magnificent.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/mozart-wink.gif" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="220" height="220"></figure><p>The sooner you free yourself of the burden of trying to be unique, and instead putting your focus on solving problems for others, the sooner you&#x2019;ll be on your way to coming up with some excellent designs.</p><p>When you&#x2019;re starting out, just focus on making something <em>work</em>. Just because Walmart uses white, blue, and orange, doesn&#x2019;t mean you can&#x2019;t. Innovation isn&#x2019;t invention out of thin air, it&#x2019;s remixing old ideas into new contexts to create new ones. Seriously, I am saving you a ton of existential stress. &#xA0;Don&#x2019;t. Sweat. It. Just focus on practicing.</p><p>With all that said&#x2026;</p><h2 id="color-isn%E2%80%99t-magic%E2%80%A6-but-it-is-powerful"><strong>Color isn&#x2019;t magic&#x2026; but it </strong><em><strong>is</strong></em><strong> powerful</strong></h2><p>Now that you hopefully have some sense of why using color effectively is important, as well as how to use color in your designs, here&#x2019;s what I&#x2019;d recommend: </p><p><strong>Have fun with it.</strong> </p><p>Keep guidelines in mind, experiment, and observe. Notice how other apps that you like are using color. Listen to your own intuition as a user. And ask others how easy it is to use, see, or read things in your designs.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.theuilab.co/content/images/2022/10/68747470733a2f2f73332e616d617a6f6e6177732e636f6d2f75707065726c696e652f637572726963756c756d2d6173736574732f70356a732f6a616b652e676966.gif" class="kg-image" alt="The UI Designer&apos;s Guide to Color: 2022" loading="lazy" width="500" height="255"></figure><p>Observing others who do something well, and then trying to recreate it, is the fastest and most reliable way to learn something new.</p><p>There&#x2019;s no shortcut to learning how to wield color like a magician, but I promise you: the more you pay attention to it in your surroundings, and the more you play around with it, the stronger those color muscles will get.</p><p>Happy coloring! &#x1F3A8;<br></p><div class="kg-card kg-callout-card kg-callout-card-grey"><div class="kg-callout-emoji">&#x2764;&#xFE0F;</div><div class="kg-callout-text">Feedback? Questions? Please share them! I&apos;m not a writer by trade and this blog post was incredibly difficult for me to write, so if you think I&apos;ve forgotten something crucial or something is unclear, please let me know at <a href="mailto:jointheuilab@gmail.com?ref=theuilab.co">jointheuilab@gmail.com</a></div></div>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>